A Finding Aid to the Tomás Ybarra-Frausto Research Material on Chicano Art, 1965-2004, in the Archives of American Art AAA.ybartoma
Archives of American Art
Tomás Ybarra-Frausto research material
1965-2004
AAA.ybartoma
Archives of American Art
30.1 Linear feet
The research material of Tomás Ybarra-Frausto, measures 30.1 linear feet and dates from 1965-2004. The collection, amassed throughout Ybarra-Frausto's long and distinguished career as a scholar of the arts and humanities, documents the development of Chicano art in the United States and chronicles Ybarra-Frausto's role as a community leader and scholar in the political and artistic Chicano movement from its inception in the 1960s to the present day.
Tomás Ybarra-Frausto
Autobiographical Note
Papelitos (little bits of paper), whether rent receipts, paid bills, or piles of personal letters, can become layered bundles of personal history. I have always been a pepenador (a scavenger) and saver of paper scraps. Diary notes, scribbled annotations, and first drafts are often useful indicators of ideas and gestation. Papelitos are the fragments of every-day life that gain expanded meaning integrated into the larger historical events of a period.
In the decade of the 1960s, I started saving ephemeral material--exhibition announcements, clippings of individual artists and of organizations fomenting a Chicano art movement. The social scenarios of the period such as marches, strikes, sit-ins, and mobilizations for social justice all spawned manifestos, posters, leaflets, and other forms of printed material. I somehow managed to assemble and protect the evanescent printed information that recorded the birth and development of Chicano art.
As I started to research and write about Chicano art and artists of the period, I continued to clip, photocopy, and preserve material given me by Mexican-American artists from throughout the nation. My idea was to form an archive that would be comprehensive rather than selective. I knew that it was the offbeat, singular piece of paper with a missing link of information that would attract the scholar.
Today, several decades after the flowering of Chicano art, there is still a lamentable paucity of research and information about this significant component of American art.
It is my fervent hope that this compendium of information will function as a resonant print and image bank for investigators of Chicano culture. Perhaps contained within the archive are the facts that will inspire new visions or revisions of Chicano art and culture--this is my fondest dream.
Dr. Tomás Ybarra-Frausto
New York City, 1998
Scope and Content Note
The research material of Tomás Ybarra-Frausto, amassed throughout his long and distinguished career as a scholar of the arts and humanities, documents the development of Chicano art in the United States. As community leader and scholar, Ybarra-Frausto played dual roles of active participant and historian in the Chicano movement, chronicling this unique political and artistic movement from its inception in the 1960s to the present day.
Deeply rooted in American history, "El Movimiento," the Chicano movement, evolved from Mexican-Americans' struggle for self-determination during the civil rights era of the 1960s. It began as a grassroots community effort that enlisted the arts in the creation of a united political and cultural constituency. Chicano artists, intellectuals, and political activists were instrumental in mobilizing the Mexican-American community for the cause of social justice, and the movement was shaped by the affirmation of a cultural identity that embraced a shared heritage with Mexico and the United States.
Just as "El Movimiento" aimed to instruct and inspire through the recollection and conservation of culture, Ybarra-Frausto's own career as scholar and historian helped to shape the intellectual discourse of the Chicano art. As a leading historian and theoretician in the field of Chicano Studies, he has written extensively on the subject, and has been instrumental in defining the canons of Chicano art. His papers are accordingly rich and varied, and they will be of great use to future scholars.
His research material, dating from 1965 to 1996, are arranged in subject files containing original writings, notes, bibliographies compiled by Ybarra-Frausto and others, exhibition catalogues, announcements, newspaper clippings and other printed material, as well as slides and photographs. Many of these files also include interview transcripts and correspondence with prominent figures in the movement. While this research collection contextualizes Chicano art within the larger framework of Latino and Latin-American culture, the bulk of the files relates specifically to Chicano visual culture. The collection also contains pertinent documentation of the Chicano civil rights movement, material on Chicano poets and writers, and research files on the wider Hispanic community, but these also appear within the context of Chicano culture in general.
Prominent among the bibliographies are the many notes and drafts related to the publication of A Comprehensive Annotated Bibliography of Chicano Art, 1965-1981 (University of California, Berkeley, 1985), which Ybarra-Frausto co-authored with Shifra Goldman. Ybarra-Frausto's files on Goldman, like other files in the collection, document his close associations and collaborations with scholars.
Art historians have traditionally found the categorization of Chicano art a difficult task. Unsure whether to classify the work as "American" or "Latin American," critics often ignored the work altogether. An outgrowth of this dilemma was the proliferation of artists, curators, and critics within the Chicano community, and the papers contain many original writings by Chicano artists about Chicano art, found in extensive files on artists that will be of particular significance to researchers. These often contain exhibition essays, dissertation proposals, and course outlines authored by the artists, along with the standard biographies, exhibition records, and reviews. Some of the files contain rare interviews conducted and transcribed by Ybarra-Frausto. Highlights include conversations with Carmen Lomas Garza, Amalia Mesa-Bains, and members of the Royal Chicano Air Force artist cooperative.
As a member of several Chicano art organizations and institutions, Ybarra-Frausto kept active records of their operation. The extensive files on the Mexican Museum and Galerie de la Raza/Studio 24, both in San Francisco, not only chronicle the history of Chicano art through the records of exhibitions and programming, but also offer case studies on the development of non-profit art institutions. The files on artist cooperatives, organizations, and exhibition spaces cover several regions of the United States, but focus on California, Texas and New York.
Two notable events in the development of Chicano art were the 1982 Califas: Chicano Art and Culture in California seminar at the University of California at Santa Cruz, and the 1990 traveling exhibition Chicano Art: Resistance and Affirmation, 1965-1985 (CARA), of which Ybarra-Frausto served as organizer and catalogue essayist. His records document the planning and development of these seminal events. Ybarra-Frausto's files on folk art, altars, posters, murals, performance art, border art, Chicana feminist art, and Southwestern and Mexican imagery (both urban and rural expressions) mirror the diverse forms and subject matter of Chicano art.
Spanning almost four decades of American culture from a Chicano perspective, these files have a unique historical value. The legacy of Chicano art and its contribution to the cultural landscape of this country, kept alive in Ybarra-Frausto's files, attests to the richness and diversity of American art.
Henry C. Estrada
Research Fellow, 1997.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as a single series of subject files. The general contents of each folder have been listed. The subject files are arranged in alphabetical order. While no two files are alike, they may contain résumés, printed material, letters, draft writings, and photographs. Unless otherwise noted, each listing represents one file folder. The abbreviation TYF was used to refer to the name Tomá Ybarra-Frausto throughtout the Series Description.
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Tomás Ybarra-Frausto in 1997, and in 2004.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Goldman, Shifra M., 1926-; Lomas Garza, Carmen; Mesa-Bains, Amalia; Mexican Museum; Royal Chicano Air Force; Studio 24 (San Francisco, Calif.); Hispanic American art--Sources; Hispanic American artists--Sources; Household shrines--Mexico; Interviews; Mexican American artists--Sources; Mexican American arts--Sources; Mexico--Religious life and customs; Photographs; Santos (Art); Slides (photographs)
- Subject Files, 1965-1997; Series 1
  - Abeyta, Ray Martín, 2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    (note card from curator Kristina Perea, curator of Abeyta's exhibition, to TYF re. the 10/15/03 Abeyta exhibition; Museum of New Mexico traveling exhibitions program calendar; color photocopies of several paintings)
  - Abrazo (see Movimiento Artistico Chicano), (newsletter) (Box 1)
  - Aceves, José, undated; (clipping) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Acosta, Dennis Ferguson, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    (letters: to Acosta from TYF, 01/08/1996, photocopy; to TYF from Acosta, 02/08/1996, fax)
  - Acosta, Manuel, 1982-1996, undated; (clippings) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Acosta-Colón, Marie, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    (note card and letter to TYF from Acosta-Colón, Director, Mexican Museum, San Francisco, 08/21/1989 and 08/19/1989)
  - Activa Unlimited, Organization, San Francisco, California, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    (letter to Jose Angel Gutierrez, curator of the L.U.P.E. - Love, Unity, Peace & Equality - Library, from Dorinda Moreno, founder L.U.P.E. Library; memo to L.U.P.E. members; clippings)
  - Address List (museum and gallery addresses), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Adelante, Exhibition Catalog, Newman Center, San José, California, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Aesthetics of Community-Based Art Making, Conference, Getty Center and the California Institute of the Arts, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    (clipping; events calendar; brochures; list of participants; letters to TYF from organizers of the conference re. his participation; copy of essay by Pedro Rodriguez, "The Changing Tides: Community-Based Cultural Arts in the USA"; program prospectus of "The Medocino People's Portrait Project, 1992-1994"; printed material relating to the production of the play "Windows...Mama, Why Is L.A. Burning?")
  - Africa's Legacy in Mexico: Photographs by Tony Gleaton, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., Catalog (see also Photography), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Aguilar, Laura, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (catalog, Laura Aguilar, Fundació "La Caixa", Barcelona, Spain, 1998; brochures)
  - Albright, Thomas, Art Critic, 1981; (clipping) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alfaro, Luis, Co-director, Latino Theatre Initiative, Los Angeles (see also La Brocha del Valle; Rodríguez, Diana), 1994-1996; (brochure, press releases, biography of Alfaro, performance programs) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alicia, Juana, 1987; (exhibition announcements) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Allen, Richard, 1987-1989; (color photographs of of Allen's work) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Almaraz, Carlos (see also: Los Four), 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    (exhibition announcements; resumes; the L.A. County Museum of Art Members' Calendar 3/74; letter to Michel Oren, East Carolina Univervsity, from Maggie Nelson of the Archives of American Art, southern California office, 12/31/1987 photocopy; clippings; catalog, Moonlight Theater: Prints and Related Works by Carlos Almaraz, Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, University of California, Los Angeles, 1991.)
  - Almasol de la Bahiá, Poetry and Musical Festival, San Francisco, 1980, undated; (invitations; announcement; calendar of events) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Altars (Box 1)
    - Altar Making (see also: Herrera, Juan Felipe), 1972, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      (TYF's notes on altars, altar-making, and altarmakers; photocopy of article by Amalia Mesa-Bains; poem by Juan Felipe Herrera; typescript of TYF's "An Affecting Presence: Chicano Altars and Altarmakers"; color photocopies of altars)
    - Altarmakers (see also: Mesa-Bains, Amalia), 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      (exhibition announcements; clippings; a letter to TYF from Cynthia Jimenez-Baca re. an essay for the catalogue of the Center for Contemporary Arts of Santa Fe's Ceremony of Memories exhibit, curated by Amalia Mesa-Bains, 11/04/1987; exhibition printed matter; Mesa-Bains' resume; TYF's notes on altars; handwritten manuscript of "Altares y Altaristas Chicanos Chicanco Altars and Altarmakers" and notes relating to it; catalogs: Familias y Fe, Museum of New Mexico, Santa Fe, NM, undated; and Thunder Over Miami: Ritual Objects of Nigerian and AfroCuban Religion, Miami-Dade Community College, Miami, FL, 1982)
    - Altars - Amalia [Mesa-Bains], 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      (catalog; TYF's notes on Mesa-Bains and her work)
    - Arte Chicano, 1980-85 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      (typescripts of articles by Amalia Mesa-Bains and TYF; clippings; transcript of an interview of Mesa-Bains by TYF; color photocopy of one of Mesa-Bains' altars; TYF's notes on altars, and his notes and drafts of paragraphs from "Altares y Altaristas Chicanos"; exhibition printed material; handmade note card from Amalia [Mesa-Bains], 03/07/1984)
    - General (see also: Mesa-Bains, Amalia; Salva, Dana), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      (catalog; color photocopies of altars; typescripts of articles by TYF and Amalia Mesa-Bains; photocopies of articles from journals)
  - Alvarez, Candida, 1993; (catalog) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Alvarez, Cecilia, 1995; (clippings) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Alvarez, Rosa Elvira, 1970; (poem) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Amado, Jesse, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    (clippings; slide list; interview of Amado by Frances Colpitt; Amado's resume and biography; exhibition announcements; photocopy letter to the Pace Roberts Foundation from Amado, 11/04/1994 concerning a project proposal and copy of proposal; artist's statement; catalogs)
  - Amaya, José, 1980, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    (letter to TYF from Amaya, 06/06/1988; clippings)
  - An American Leader - Cesar E. Chavez, Exhibition, Latino Museum, Los Angeles, California, 2000; (exhibition announcement/invitation) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - American Voices: Latino Photographers in the United States, Exhibition, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (see also Americanos: Latino Life in the United States; Buitrón, Robert; Photography), 1992, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    (curators' biographies, Charles Biasiny-Rivera; Robert Buitrón; Kathy Vargas; Ricardo Viera); exhibition brochure; copies of letters sent to Susana Leval, Chief Curator of El Museo de Barrio, Charles Biasiny-Rivera, EN FOCO, Inc., and Timothy McClimon from Wendy Watriss, Fotofest curator, 12/07/1992; project notes)
  - Americanos: Latino Life in the United States/Americanos: La vida de los latinos en los Estado Unidos, Exhibition, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (see also American Voices: Latino Photographers in the United States; photography), 1999; (press release; exhibition brochures) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Americas 2001, Magazine, Vol.1, no. 5, March/April 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Amezcua, Consuelo González (Chelo) Artist (1903-1975), 1968-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    (clippings; letter to TYF from Amezcua, 10/04/1971; photograph, unidentified; exhibition announcement; catalogs, one signed by the artist with a note to TYF)
  - Amor en Aztlán, Acrosscultural Fiesta, University of California at Santa Cruz, 1987; (calendar of events) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ancient Roots/New Visions, Exhibition, Tucson Museum of Art, Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery, and Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, Illinois, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    (catalogs; clippings; calendar of events; TYF's notes on 2 small slips of paper on history of and influences on Mexican American literature)
  - Andrade, Bruno, 1998; (exhibition announcement) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Anzaldua, Carlos G., circa 1985; (resume) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Aquí: 27 Latin American Artists Living and Working in the United States, Exhibition, Fisher Gallery, University of Southern California, 1984; (catalog) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Aquí y Allá, Exhibition, Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery, 1990; (calendar of events, exhibition announcement, catalog) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Archiving the Latino Arts Before It Is Too Late,", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    (issue of Latino Policy & Issues Brief, UCLA Chicano Studies Research Center, Los Angeles, California, no.6 April 2003)
  - Archuleta, Felipe Benito, 1979, 1986; (clippings) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Archuleta-Sagel, Terésa, circa 1981-1983; (postcards of the artist's work; biography) (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Arismendi, Connie, 1991, 1998; (exhibition announcement; brochure) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Arizona (Box 1)
    - Movimiento Artistico Del Rio Salado (MARS), 1978-1991; (see also: Movimiento Artistico Del Rio Salado; Box 30) (Box 1, Folder 45)
      (Dolores Rivas Bahti's resume; grant application for continuation of Movimiento Artistico Del Rio Salado Visiting Artist program; calendar of events; artist biography of Alfredo Arreguin written by TYF; clippings; TYF's notes on "Contra Colonialismo: Colombian Exchange"; catalog; oversize poster)
    - Chicano Art, 1965-circa 1990s, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
      (Hispanic Research Center, Arizona State University brochure; organization information sheets for: the United Chicano Artists, the Mechicano Art Center, the Goaz Art Gallery, the Centro Joaquin Murietta de Aztlan, and the Mexican American Center for Creative Arts; clippings; TYF's note on Arizon Chicano art materials)
  - Arizona State University, Latin American Art Collection Guide, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    (typed guide to the ASU Latin American Art Collection)
  - Ariztlan, Newsletter, National Endowment for the Arts and the Arizona Commission for the Arts (see also: Baca, Judith; Buitrón, Robert; Guerrero, Zarco; Rios, Richard and Graciela; Valle del Sol), 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    (vol. 2, no. 2 1982; March 1985; June 1985; October 1985; January 1986; August 1986; and March 1987; the 1982 issue includes pieces on Valle del Sol, Inc. of Phoenix and the 1st Ariztlan Hispanic Arts Conference, and an article written by Robert Buitron; March 1985 issue features an article on El Zarco; August 1986 issue contains articles about Judy Baca and Richard and Graciela Rios)
  - Armendariz, Ricky, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    (resume, clippings, slides of his work dated from 1995-1997)
  - Arredondo, Jaime M., circa 1990, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    (invitation, with a note to TYF written by Arredondo; Arredondo's application for fellowship tenure, Michigan Society of Fellows; research proposal; typescript of "The Apocalyptic Vision of the Aztecs as it relates to Superstitions, Omens and Fortune-Telling" by Arredondo)
  - Arreguín, Alfredo (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1974-2004 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence and Writings, 1974-1995 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      (letters to TYF from Arreguín, 05/18/1983, 05/20/1986, 07/03/1991; notes to TYF from Arreguín, 12/07/1994, circa 12/1996, undated; note to TYF from Susie [Susan Lytle], 03/23/1995; photocopy of letter to Arreguín from TYF, 07/15/1991; letter and photocopies of letters to Arreguín from: Charles Royer, Office of the Mayor of the City of Seattle,12/11/1979; Nan Woolridge, Bainbridge Island Arts Council, 04/23/1987; and Virginia Mecklenburg and Andrew Connors, both of the National Museum of American Art, 06/15/1992, 11/08/1994, 01/12/1995; press release; photocopy of a handwritten draft of an article by TYF about the artist; essay by Mary Motian-Meadows; photocopies of art; written pieces for exhibition catalogs)
    - Exhibitions, 1974-2003 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      (exhibition announcements; catalogs; book, Alfredo Arreguín: El Universad Vegetal, Animal y Humano de un Pintor Moreliano, Morelia, Mich., México, Universidad Michoacana de San Nicolas de Hidalgo, Centro de Estudios sobre la Cultura Nicolaita, 1989; postcards of Arreguín's works)
  - Arriba Newsletter, October 1983, September 1984, circa May 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Art of the Other Mexico: Sources and Meanings, Exhibition, Mexican Fine Arts Center Museum, Chicago, IL, 1993; (exhibition announcement; catalog; clippings; invitation) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Art of the Santera, Exhibition, Museum of International Folk Art, Museum of New Mexico, Santa Fe, New Mexico (see also: Museum of International Folk Art), circa 1992, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    (catalog; clippings)
  - Arte Chicano Bibliography (see also: Bibliographic Notes), circa 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    (printed matter relating to TYF's A Comprehensive Annotated Bibliography of Chicano Art, 1965-1981; typed drafts with handwritten notes; handwritten drafts; clippings; photocopies of bibliographic citations; notes; Chicano Studies Library, UC Berkeley brochures; note to TYF from Carolyn Soto of the Chicano Studies Library, 12/03/1986)
  - Arte Chicano Chronology, 1982, undated; (see also: Box 30) (Box 1, Folder 58)
    (TYF's notes on the chronology of Chicano art, beginning with 1968, El Arte De Pocho Exhibition, and concluding in 1977, Inauguration of the Mexican Museum; handwritten draft of the chronology; a list of "Artistes Chicanos"; oversize poster advertizing a play about barrios in San José)
  - El Arte Chicano de Hoy, Exhibition, San José Museum of Art, San José, California, 1974; (catalog) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Arte Chicano/Latino: Imagenes en el Siglo des SIDA, Exhibition, University of Colorado, Bolder, Colorado (see also: Colorado), 1994; (exhibition brochure/catalog) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Arte Hispano, Organization, Tucson, Arizona, 1988; (exhibition announcement) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Arte Picante: Contemporary Chicano Art, Chicano Arts Festival, University of California at San Diego, 1975-1976; (see also: OV 32) (Box 1, Folder 62)
    (clippings; oversize poster/entry form; exhibition announcement; photocopy of the calendar of events, with note to TYF from T[ino] V[illanueva], 1/27/76)
  - Artes Plásticas, circa 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    (photocopied article defining "Artes Plásticas"; photocopies of articles on literature, philosophy, and various artists and other figures in chicano/latino culture, José María Arguedas, Manuel Puig, Ernst Fischer)
  - Artes Visuales, Magazine, Mexico City, Mexico, June 1981 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Artino Arts Group, Organization, Los Angeles, California, 2003; (exhibition announcement) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - "The Artist As Cultural Worker: Art Production and Politics,", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    (typescript of address given by Ramón Favela at the Artistic and Cultural Identity in Latin America conference)
  - Artists and the Chicano Movement, Kellie Jones (see also: Gómez-Peña, Guillermo; Mesa-Bains, Amalia), undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
    (essay, excerpt from a longer, as yet unpublished, paper entitled Amalia Mesa-Bains and Guillermo Gómez-Peña: Artists's Histories and the Chicano Movement)
  - Artists' Books, circa 1977; (see also: Box 30) (Box 1, Folder 68)
    (publications list from Printed Matter, Inc.; clippings; oversize poster)
  - Artists Call Against U.S. Intervention in Central America, 1979, 1983; (clippings; progress report; general notices to members) (Box 1, Folder 69)